Guide to the Le Keux Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Le Keux correspondence
1811-1879
OSB MSS 27
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection consists of professional correspondence of John, Henry and John Henry Le Keux, including letters from publishers, artists, fellow engravers, patrons, and prospective students. Among the correspondents are Robert Batty, Edwin Guest, Augustus Charles Pugin, and Dawson Turner. A letter by George Doo encloses a copy of the Associated Society of Engravers' plan for publishing their National Gallery collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
.[Insert text here]
LE KEUX FAMILY
John Le Keux (1783-1846) and his younger brother Henry Le Keux (1787-1868) were apprenticed to the architectural engraver James Basire, and both produced a wide variety of architectural and views engravings for various publications, including works by Neale, Pugin, and J. M. W. Turner. Henry Le Keux abandoned engraving work for the crape manufacturing business in 1838, but John continued to execute commissions until shortly before his death in 1846. John's eldest son, John Henry Le Keux (1812-1896), also became an architectural engraver; his works include plates in Ruskin's Stones of Venice (1851) and Modern Painters (1888).
Scope and Contents
The Le Keux Correspondence consists of business letters addressed to John, Henry, and John Henry Le Keux, along with a few letters by each. The papers span the dates 1811-1879 and have been arranged alphabetically by correspondent in a single series.
The letters' authors include fellow engravers, prospective students, artists, publishers, and patrons of works to which the Le Keux contributed. Authors include Robert Batty, A. C. Pugin, Dawson Turner, and Alaric Alexander Watts.
Engravers -- Great Britain; Engraving -- Great Britain; Publishers and publishing -- Great Britain; Engravers -- Great Britain; Batty, Robert, 1788 or 1789-1848; Bliss, Philip, 1787-1857; Bridgewater, Francis Henry Egerton, Earl of, 1756-1829; Cooke, George, 1781-1834; Doo, George Thomas, 1800-1886; Finden, W. (William), 1787-1852; Guest, Edwin, 1800-1880; Le Keux, Henry, 1787-1868; Le Keux, John Henry, 1812-1896; Le Keux, John, 1783-1846; Nichols, John Gough, 1806-1873; Pugin, Augustus, 1762-1832; Turner, Dawson, 1775-1858; Wyatt, M. Digby, Sir (Matthew Digby), 1820-1877
- Correspondence, Series I
  - ACKERMANN, RUDOLPH, 1764-1834
    - AL to Henry Le Keux, Strand, 1825 Apr 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ACKERMANN, RUDOLPH, D. 1868
    - AL to J. H. Le Keux, S. A., 1854 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - ARCH, JOHN ARTHUR
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, London, 1830 Dec 29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - BATTY, ROBERT, 1788-1848
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, Connaught Square, 1830 Sep 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - BELL, J. A.
    - Receipt (holograph, signed) for payment for drawings supplied to John Le Keux, London, 1863 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Scope and Contents
      Eight drawings of Cambridge buildings.
  - BLISS, PHILIP, 1787-1857
    - 3 ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Oxford, Brighton, 1855, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Oxford engravings.
  - BLORE, EDWARD, 1787-1879
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, Welbeck Street, 1838 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - BOONE, THOMAS
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Bond Street, [n.y.] Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - BRIDGEWATER, FRANCIS HENRY EGERTON
    [8TH EARL OF, 1756-1829]
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, Bridgewater, 1820 Mar 30 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - CLARKE, JOSEPH
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Saffron Walden, 1856 Jan 11 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - CLUTTERBUCK, ROBERT, 1772-1831
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, London, 1815 Nov 14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - COOKE, EDWARD WILLIAM, 1811-1880
    - ALS to John Henry Le Keux, Kensington, [n.y.] Jan 22 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - COOKE, GEORGE, 1781-1834
    - 2 ALS to Henry Le Keux, [n.p.], [1816?], 1821 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Engravings in hand.
  - COXE, HENRY OCTAVIUS, 1811-1881
    - ALS to John Henry Le Keux, Bodleian Library, 1866 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - CURTIS, E. J.
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Barnsbury Park, 1857 Dec 30 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - DAVIDSON, C.
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Reigate, [1861] (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Sent a drawing for Dr. Magoon.
  - DE LA MOTTE, PHILIP H.
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Kings College, London, 1861 Oct 10 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - DOO, GEORGE T., 1800-1886
    - Memorandum of draft resolution by the Associated Society of Engravers, [London], 1827 Jan 15 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Meeting at John Le Keux's.
  - DUNCAN, EDWARD, 1804-1882
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Mornington Place, 1846 Mar 6 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - DUNCOMBE, G.
    - Memorandum to J. H. Le Keux from the Board of Trade, 1855 Feb 2 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - FINDEN, WILLIAM, 1787-1852
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, London, 1831 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - FRASER, JAMES, D. 1841
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Regent Street, 1839 Dec 4 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - GOODALL, EDWARD, 1795-1870
    - ALS to John Le Keux, Mornington Crescent, 1845 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - GORHAM, GEORGE, CORNELIUS, 1787-1857
    - 2 ALS and 2 notes, unsigned, to J. H. Le Keux, Brampford Speke, 1856-57 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Illustrations for Reformation Gleanings [?].
  - GREENWELL, DORA, 1821-1882
    - ALS to Mrs. J. H. Le Keux, [n.p.], [n.y.] Dec 29 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - GUEST, EDWIN, 1800-1880
    - AL to J. H. Le Keux, Sandford Park, 1861 Aug 19 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Regarding map received from Mr. C. C. Babington.
    - 2 ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Oxon, 1862 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Map of western England.
  - HARPER, THOMAS
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Camden Rd., N. W., 1862 Dec 13 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - HEATON, CHARLES WILSON, 1817-1881
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Jesus College, Oxford, 1862 Dec 4 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - HOWELL, JOHN, 1788-1863
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, [n.p.], 1855 Aug 3 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - HUGO, THOMAS, 1820-1876
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Bishopsgate St. Within, 1855 Feb 19 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - JONES, WILLIAM BASIL TICKELL, BP. OF
    [ST. DAVIDS, 1822-1897]
    - ALS to Freeman & Jones, University College, Oxford, [1856?] Dec 13 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Endorses cheque for Mr. Le Keux.
  - LE KEUX, HENRY, 1787-1868
    - ALS to John Le Keux, Dorset St., 1820 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Charles Pye transmits apology by John Britton.
    - ALS to [John Henry Le Keux], Bosking, 1853 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - ALS to [Longmans], Dorset St., 1820 Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      With comment to John Britton [?] by T. Huntsman of Longsmans.
  - LE KEUX, JOHN, 1783-1846
    - ALS to Deightons, Bourne End, 1844 Oct 26 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, Pentonville, 1826 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      With receipt added by Neale for the copper plates.
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, Harmondsworth, 1838 Feb 6 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - ALS to John Henry Le Keux, Bourne End (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - ALS to Mr. Tilt, Harmondsworth, 1833 Jul 9 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - LE KEUX, JOHN HENRY, 1812-1896
    - 2 ALS to George Rutland, Durham, 1873 Jul 7-8 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      A sale of books, etc.
  - LIZARS, WILLIAM HOME, 1788-1859
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, Edinburgh, 1819 Aug 6 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      Delivered by a friend, Mr. Stewart, Engraver.
  - LODDIGES, GEORGE, 1784-1846
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Hackney, 1834 Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - MAGOON, ELMER L.
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, New York, 1856 Oct 7 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - MASON, A. J.
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, [n.p.], [n.y.] Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - MAYER, JOSEPH, 1803-1886
    - 2 ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Liverpool, 1856 Feb, Mar (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Prints and particulars of artists.
  - NASH, FREDERICK, 1782-1856
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, London, [1816?] Aug 8 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - NESBITT, ALEXANDER
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Torquay, [n.y.] Jan 3 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - NICHOLS, JOHN GOUGH, 1806-1873
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Parliament St., [1854?] Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Letter, in another hand and signed Sylvanus Urban, to J. H. Le Keux, Strand, 1860 Aug 16 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - OUVRY, FREDERIC, 1814-1881
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Somerset House, 1855 Mar 13 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - OWEN, [N?] C.
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Board of Trade, London, 1854 Aug 12 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      Space at Paris Exhibition; reference to Henry Le Keux.
  - PACKE, CHARLES WILLIAM, 1792-1867
    - AL to John Le Keux, Whitehall, [n.y.] Mar 23 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      Engraving crest.
  - PALEY, FREDERICK APTHROP, 1815-1888
    - ALS to John Le Keux, Cambridge, [ca.1845] Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 54)
      Discussion with Camden Society Committee, Ecclesiological.
  - PARKER, JOHN HENRY, 1806-1884
    - ALS to John Le Keux, Oxford, 1836 Nov 9 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - PEASON, R. KYRKE
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Kidwelly, 1857 Aug 31 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - PEPPER, JOHN HENRY, 1821-1900
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Royal Polytechnic Inst., 1855 Sep 28 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - PLANCHE, JAMES ROBINSON, 1796-1880
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Sackville St., Piccadilly, 1855 Jan 27 (Box 1, Folder 58)
      Mr. Baily has informed the Council [of British Archaeological Assn.].
  - PROUT, SAMUEL, 1783-1852
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, Brixton, [ca.1825] Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - PUGIN, AUGUSTUS CHARLES, 1762-1832
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, Southampton St., 1817 Jun 30 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - PYE, John, 1782-1874
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, Cirencester Place, 1838 Apr 23 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      With outline in pencil of reply on p. 1.
  - REINAGLE, RAMSEY RICHARD, 1775-1862
    - ALS to John Le Keux, London, [1834 Jun 2] (Box 1, Folder 62)
      Written on verso of printed notice of prints of "Sunrise".
  - RODWELL & MARTIN
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, Bond St., 1821 Nov 20 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - SCHIRMER, M.
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, London Coffeehouse, [n.y.] Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - SCOTT, SIR GEORGE GILBERT, 1811-1878
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Spring Gardens, 1857 Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - SHARPE, EDMUND, 1809-1877
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, St. James's Place, 1848 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - SHAW, Henry, 1800-1873
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Southampton Row, 1854 Apr 7 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - SMITH W. COLLINGWOOD
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Pimlico, [1854 or later] (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - THOMPSON, WILLIAM, ABP. OF YORK, 1819-1890
    - 2 ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Oxford, 1861, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 69)
      Drawings of Oxford and payment.
  - TILT, CHARLES
    - 2 ALS to John Le Keux, Fleet St., 1842 May, Jun (Box 1, Folder 70)
      Details of publishing business.
  - TITFORD, WILLIAM JOWITT
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, [London], 1811 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - TUCKER, CHARLES
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Suffolk St., 1850 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - TURNER, DAWSON, 1775-1858
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, Yarmouth, 1821 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - VARLEY, CORNELIUS, 1781-1873
    - Signature on a note of admittance for J. H. Le Keux, 1839 Mar 4 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - WALKER, THOMAS LARKINS, d. 1860
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Leicester, 1855 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - WATTS, ALARIC ALEXANDER, 1797-1864
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, Torrington Square, 1827 Nov 21 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - WEALE, John, 1791-1862
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, High Holborn, 1861 Jun 18 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - WHITE, ALFRED
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, West Drayton, 1853 Aug 16 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - WILD, CHARLES BEARD, 1781-1835
    - ALS to Henry Le Keux, New Bond St., 1815 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - ALS to John Le Keux, Mortimer St., [n.y.] Oct 31 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - WILLIAMS, THOMAS
    - 2 ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Northumberland House, 1860 Jan, Feb (Box 1, Folder 81)
      Plates for the Duke of Northumberland, C. H. Hartshorn, and Albert Way.
  - WILMORE, ARTHUR
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, [n.p.], 1872 Sep 7 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - WRIGHT, THOMAS, 1810-1877
    - ALS to J. H. Le Keux, Brompton, [n.y.] Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - WYATT, SIR MATTHEW DIGBY, 1820-1877
    - 2 memoranda to J. H. Le Keux, London, 1850-51 (Box 1, Folder 84)
      From the office of Sir M. Digby Wyatt.